Finding Aid for Jasper Green Pennington papers, 1969-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jasper Green Pennington papers 1969-2007
Pennington, Jasper Green.
0724 Aa 2
Episcopal clergyman at St. Luke's Episcopal Church, Ypsilanti, Michigan; also local historian of Washtenaw County, Michigan
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Jasper Green Pennington (donor no. 9832 ) and has come to the library in multiple accessions.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Jasper Green Pennington, Episcopal clergyman, was born in 1939. He was ordained to the priesthood in 1973 and became rector of St. Luke's Episcopal Church, Ypsilanti, Michigan, in 1983, a position he held until his retirement in 2001. During his retirement he served at other Episcopal churches in Southeastern Michigan, including St. Clement's in Inkster, Michigan. Pennington has had a great interest in historic preservation, and has been active in the restoration of Ypsilanti's Highland Cemetery, and as a member of the Washtenaw County Historic District Commission.
The Pennington papers relates primarily to his activities with the Washtenaw County Historic District Commission. Other materials concern general Episcopal Church activities in Inkster and Ypsilanti, Michigan. Of special interest are the historical research papers prepared by Pennington on Episcopal and Ypsilanti topics.
Subjects:
Pennington, Jasper Green.; African American churches--Michigan--Inkster.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Inkster.; Inkster (Mich.)--Church history.; St. Clement's Episcopal Church (Inkster, Mich.); St. Luke's Episcopal Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Clergy--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Historic preservation--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Washtenaw County Historic District Commission.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Church history.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--History.
- Washtenaw County Historic District Commission
  - Minutes and related materials 1998-2001, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Monthly files: agenda and minutes, e-mails, print-outs, reports
    - 2004, 11 folders (Box 1)
    - 2005, 11 folders (Box 1)
    - 2006, 11 folders (Box 1)
    - January-July 2007, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Township / City files: brochures, collected material
    - Augusta (Box 1)
    - Chelsea (Box 1)
    - Dexter (Box 1)
    - Manchester (Box 1)
    - Northfield (Box 1)
    - Pittsfield (Box 1)
    - Saline (Box 1)
    - Sharon (Box 1)
    - Superior (Box 1)
    - Webster (Box 1)
    - Ypsilanti (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous administrative
    - Appointment to commission (Box 1)
    - Bridges and highways (Box 1)
    - Historic Preservation Ordinance (Box 1)
    - Proposals, various (Box 1)
    - Web Page (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Historic District Study Committee Reports
    - Delhi Bridge Historic District 2006 (Box 1)
    - Geddesburg 1999 (Box 1)
    - Geer -- Milton and Kittie Geer House, Superior Township, preliminary and final reports 2001 (Box 1)
    - Gordon Hall built for Judge Samuel W. Dexter, Webster Township
      - Preliminary and final reports 2001 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous: clippings, print-outs (Box 2)
    - McCormick Farm -- William and Jane McCormick Farm, Superior Township, preliminary and final reports 2001-2002 (Box 2)
    - McMahon Springs Historic District, Ann Arbor Township, preliminary report 2003 (Box 2)
    - Manchester Historic District: Exchange Place, preliminary report 2006 (Box 2)
    - Merriman Farm, Manchester Township, final report 2004 (Box 2)
    - Old Zion Parsonage, Freedom Township, preliminary and final report 2002-2003 (Box 2)
    - Popkins School Historic District, Ann Arbor Township
      - Preliminary report 2000 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous -- reconstruction proposal, memorandum, etc. (Box 2)
      - Pray -- Esek Pray House, Superior Township, preliminary report undated (Box 2)
- Other Activities
  - Episcopal Church, Diocese of Michigan
    - Altar Guild (Box 2)
    - Ordination of Women -- clippings and articles (Box 2)
    - Diocesan Ecumenical Commission 1970s-1990s, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - St. Clement's Episcopal Church (Inkster, Mich.)
    - Newsletters 1984-1996 (Box 2)
    - Lenten and other meditations for 2005 by Rev. Jasper Green Pennington (Box 2)
  - Highland Cemetery, Ypsilanti, Michigan: minutes, memorandum, miscellaneous, 1990s- circa 2004 (Box 2)
- Research Papers on local and family history (variously named Pennington Papers or Ypsilanti Papers
  - John Challis (1907-1974): America's First Harpsichord Builder and Citizen of Ypsilanti, Michigan (Notes for an Article) 1985 (Box 2)
  - Silas Freeman (1797-1854) and Dr. Andrew Cornish (1782-1846): Founders of St. Luke's Church, Ypsilanti, Michigan in 1830 1989 (Box 2)
  - The Stained Glass Windows of St. Luke's Episcopal Church, Ypsilanti, Michigan 1990 (Box 2)
  - The Horatio Blackmore Lewis Family of Ypsilanti, Michigan 1992 (Box 2)
  - The Reverend John Andrew Wilson, D.D., (1810-1885), VI Rector of St. Luke's Episcopal Church, Ypsilanti, Michigan, 1847-1884 1994 (Box 2)
  - The Reverend Henry P. Powers, (1805-1865), V Rector of St. Luke's Church, Ypsilanti, Michigan, 1840-1846 1995 (Box 2)
  - Anglicans in Early Detroit: Some Threads in the Early Fabric of the Church September 22, 1996 (Box 2)
  - James Lewis Glen (1814-1876) and Highland Cemetery, Ypsilanti, Michigan 1997 (Box 2)
  - Adaline Ballou Scovil of Ypsilanti Michigan, (1830-1913) 1998 (Box 2)
  - The Reverend Alanson W. Welton (1790-1822), First Episcopal Priest in the Michigan Territory 2001 (Box 2)
  - The Episcopal Church and the Some Missionaries to the Indians of Michigan 2000 (Box 2)
  - The Reverend William Hothersall Gardam, DCL, DD, (1851-1914), Eleventh Rector of Historic Saint Luke's Episcopal Church, Ypsilanti, Michigan, 1896-1914. 2002 (Box 2)
  - Notes on the Descendants of Darius Comstock and Anna Pennington of Lenawee, County, Michigan 2003 (Box 2)
  - Pipe Organs of the Churches & Chapels of the Ypsilanti Historic District 1996, 2003 (Box 2)
  - D. Felix Lamond 1862-1937, "A Musicians Musician" (Notes for an article), 1997 (Box 2)
Related Material
There is a separate website for the Jasper Green Pennington library and archives: jaspergreenpennington.com